<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sixe idillia that is, sixe small, or petty poems, or æglogues, chosen out of the right famous Sicilian poet Theocritus, and translated into English verse.</title>
            <title>Idylls. English</title>
            <author>Theocritus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838408</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13654)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1118:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sixe idillia that is, sixe small, or petty poems, or æglogues, chosen out of the right famous Sicilian poet Theocritus, and translated into English verse.</title>
                  <title>Idylls. English</title>
                  <author>Theocritus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>An English translation of Theocritus' Idyllia.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2784:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2784:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIXE IDILLIA</p>
            <p>THAT IS, SIXE SMALL, OR PETTY POEMS, OR ÆGLOGVES, CHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the right famous Sicilian Poet THEOCRITVS, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Engliſh verſe.</p>
            <q>Dum defluat amnis.</q>
            <p>PRINTED At Oxford, by IOSEPH BARNES. 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2784:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>Libenter hic, &amp; omnis exantlabitur</l>
            <l>Labor, in tuæ spem gratiæ.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2784:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SIXE</hi> IDILLIA, CHOSEN OVT OF THE famous Sicilian Poet <hi>THEOCRITVS,</hi> and <hi>tranſlated into Engliſh verſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="play">
               <head>THE VIII. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>Menalcas a Shephearde, and Daphnis a Netehearde, two Sicilian Iads, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontending who ſhould ſing beſt, pawne their whiſtles, and chooſe a Gotehearde, to be their Iudge. Who giueth ſentence on Daphnis his ſide. The thing is imagined to be don in the Ile of Sicily by the Sea ſhore of whoſe ſinging, this Idillion is called BVCOLIASTAE, that is, Singers of a Neteheards ſong.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>BVCOLIASTÆ.</head>
               <head type="sub">DAPHNIS. MENALCAS. GOTEHEARDE.</head>
               <stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ITH</hi> louely Netehearde Daphnis on the hills, they ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Shepehearde Menalcas mett, vpon a ſummers daie.</l>
                  <l>Both yuth fullſtriplings, both had yeallow heades of heare,</l>
                  <l>In whiſtling both, and both in ſinging ſkilfull weare.</l>
                  <l>Menalcas firſt, behoulding Daphnis, thus beſpake.</l>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>Wilt thou in ſinging, Netehearde Daphnis, vndertake</l>
                  <l>To ſtriue with me? for I affirme, that at my will</l>
                  <l>I can thee paſse. thus Daphnis aunſwerde on the hill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>Whiſtler Menalcas, thou ſhalt neuer me excell</l>
                  <l>In ſinging, though to death with ſinging thou ſhouldſt ſwell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <p>Then wilt thou ſee, and ſomething for the victor wage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <p>I will both ſee, and ſomething for the victor gage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <p>What therefore ſhal we pawne, that for vs maie befit?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:3"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile pawne a calfe, a wennell lambe laie thou to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile pawne no lambe, for both my Syre and Mother fell</l>
                  <l>Are verie hard, and all my ſheepe at evne they tell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <p>What then? what ſhall he gaine that winns the victore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>A gallant Whiſtell which J made with notes thriſe three,</l>
                  <l>Joinde with white waxe, both evne belowe and evne aboue,</l>
                  <l>This will I laie, my Fathers thinges I will not moue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>And J a Whiſtle haue with notes thriſe three arowe,</l>
                  <l>Joinde with white waxe, both evne aboue, and evne belowe.</l>
                  <l>J latelie framde it, for this finger yet doth ake</l>
                  <l>With pricking, which a ſplinter of a reede did make.</l>
                  <l>But who ſhall be our Iudge, and giue vs audience?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>What if we call this Goteheard heere, not far from hence,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe dog doth barke harde by the kids?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <l>the luſtie boies</l>
                     <l>Did call him, and the Gotehearde came to heare their toies.</l>
                     <l>The luſtie boies did ſing, the Gotehearde iudgement gaue.</l>
                     <l>Menalcas firſt by lot vnto his whiſtle braue</l>
                     <l>Did ſing a Neteheards ſong, and Neteheard Daphnis than</l>
                     <l>Did ſing by courſe, but firſt Menalcas thus began.</l>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>Yee Groues, and Brookes deuine, if on his reede</l>
                  <l>Menalcas euer ſung a pleaſant laie,</l>
                  <l>Fat me theſe Lambes; if Daphnis here wil feede</l>
                  <l>His calfes, let him haue paſture toe I praie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>Yee pleaſant Springs, and Plants, would Daphnis had</l>
                  <l>As ſweete a voice as haue the Nightingales;</l>
                  <l>Feede me this heard, and if the ſheepeheards lad</l>
                  <l>Menalcas cums, let him haue al the dales.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis euer ſpring, their meades are euer gaie,</l>
                  <l>There ſtrowt the bags, their ſheepe are fatly fed</l>
                  <l>Where Daphne cums; go ſhe awaie,</l>
                  <l>Then both the ſheepheard there, and graſſe is ded.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:3"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>There both the Ewes, and Gotes bring forth their twins,</l>
                  <l>Their Bees doe fil their hiues, their Okes are hie</l>
                  <l>Where Milo treades; when he awaie begins</l>
                  <l>To goe, both Neteheard, and the Nete waxe drie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>O huſband of the Gotes! O wood ſo hie!</l>
                  <l>O kids, come to this brooke, for he is there;</l>
                  <l>Thou with the broken hornes, tel Milo shie,</l>
                  <l>That Proteûs kept Sea-calfes, though God he were.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor Pelops kingdome may J craue, nor gould,</l>
                  <l>Nor to outrunne the windes vpon a lea;</l>
                  <l>But in this caue Ile ſing, with thee in hould,</l>
                  <l>Both looking on my ſheepe, and on the ſea.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>A tempeſt marreth trees, and drought a ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Snares vnto foules, to beaſtes, netts are a ſmarte,</l>
                  <l>Loue ſpoiles a man. O Ioue, alone his ſting</l>
                  <l>J haue not felt, for thou a louer art.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <l>Thus ſung theſe boies by courſe, with voices ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Menalcas then began a latter ſong.</l>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>MENALCAS.</speaker>
                  <l>Wolfe, ſpare my kids, and ſpare my fruitful ſheepe,</l>
                  <l>And hurt me not, though but a lad theſe flockes J gide;</l>
                  <l>Lampur my dog, art thou indeede ſo ſound aſleepe?</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt not ſleepe, while thou art by thy Maſters ſide.</l>
                  <l>My ſheepe, fear not to eate the tender graſſe at will,</l>
                  <l>Nor when it ſpringeth vp againe, ſee that you faile;</l>
                  <l>Goe to, and feede apace, and al your bellies fill,</l>
                  <l>That part your Lambes my haue, and part my milking paile.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <l>Then Daphnis in his turne ſweetly began to ſing.</l>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>DAPHNIS.</speaker>
                  <l>And me not long agoe faire Daphne wiſtle eide</l>
                  <l>As J droue by, and ſaid J was a paragone;</l>
                  <l>Nor then indeede to her I churliſhlie replide,</l>
                  <l>But looking on the ground, my way ſtil held J one.</l>
                  <l>Sweete is a cowcalfes voice, and ſweete her breath doth ſmell,</l>
                  <l>A bulcalfe, and a cow doe lowe ful pleaſantlie;</l>
                  <l>Tis ſweete in ſummer by a ſpring abrode to dwell,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:4"/>
                  <l>Acornes become the Oke, apples the Appletree,</l>
                  <l>And calfes the kine, and kine, the Neteheard much ſet out.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <l>Thus ſung theſe Yuthes; the Gotehearde thus did ende the dout.</l>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>GOTEHEARD.</speaker>
                  <l>O Daphnis, what a dulcet mouth, and voice thou haſt?</l>
                  <l>Tis ſweeter thee to heare, than honie-combes to taſt.</l>
                  <l>Take thee theſe pipes, for thou in ſinging doſt excell.</l>
                  <l>Jf me a Gotehearde thou wilt teach to ſing ſo well,</l>
                  <l>This broken horned Goate, on thee beſtowe I will,</l>
                  <l>Which to the verie brimm, the paile doth euer fill.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <l>So then was Daphnis glad, and lept, and clapt his handes,</l>
                  <l>And danſt, as doth a fawne, when by the damm he ſtandes.</l>
                  <l>Menalcas greeud, the thing his mind did much diſmaie,</l>
                  <l>And ſad as Bride he was, vpon the marrige daie.</l>
                  <l>Since then, among the Shepeheards, Daphnis chiefe was had,</l>
                  <l>And tooke a Nimphe to wife, when he was but a lad.</l>
               </stage>
               <p>DAPHNIS his Embleme. <hi>Me tamen vrit amor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MENALCAS his Embleme.<hi>At hæc Daphne for ſan probet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GOTEHEARDES Embleme. <hi>Est minor nemo niſi comparatus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>THE XI. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>Theocritus wrote this Idillion to Nicias a learned Phyſition. wherein he ſheweth by the example of Polyphemus, a Gyant in Sicilie, of the race of the Cyclopes, who loued the water Nymph Galatea, that ther is no medecine ſo ſoueraigne againſt loue, as is Poetry. Of whoſe loue-ſong, as this Idillio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is termed Cyclops, ſo he was called Cyclops, becauſe he had but one eie, that ſtood like a circle in the middeſt of his forehead.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>CYCLOPS.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> Nicias, there is no other remedie for loue,</l>
                  <l>With ointing, or with ſprinkling on, that euer I could proue,</l>
                  <l>Beſide the Muſes nine. this pleaſant medſun of the minde</l>
                  <l>Growes among men, and ſeems but lite, yet verie hard to finde.</l>
                  <l>As well I wote you knowe, who are in Phiſicke ſuch a leeche,</l>
                  <l>And of the Muſes ſo belov'd. the cauſe of this my ſpeeche,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:4"/>
                  <l>A Cyclops is, who liued heere with vs right welthele,</l>
                  <l>That anchent Polyphem, when firſt he loued Galate;</l>
                  <l>When with a briſtled beard, his chin and cheekes firſt clothed were.</l>
                  <l>He lov'd her not, with roſes, apples, or with curled heare,</l>
                  <l>But with the Furies rage. al other thinges he little plide.</l>
                  <l>For often to their fould, from pastures green, without a guide</l>
                  <l>His ſheepe returned home, when all the while he ſinging laie</l>
                  <l>Jn honor of his loue, and on the ſhore conſumde awaie</l>
                  <l>From morning vntil night, ſicke of the wound, faſt by the hart,</l>
                  <l>Which mighty Venus gaue, and in his liuer ſtucke the dart.</l>
                  <l>For which, this remedie he found, that ſitting oftentimes</l>
                  <l>Vpon a rocke, and looking on the Sea, he ſung theſe rimes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Galatea faire, why doſt thou ſhun thy louer true?</l>
                  <l>More tender than a Lambe, more white than cheeſe when it is new,</l>
                  <l>More wanton than a calfe, more ſharpe than grapes vnripe I finde.</l>
                  <l>You vſe to come, when pleaſant ſleepe my ſenſes all doe binde.</l>
                  <l>But you are gone againe, when pleaſant ſleepe dooth leaue mine eie,</l>
                  <l>And as a ſheep you run, that on the plaine a Woolfe doth ſpie.</l>
                  <l>J then began to loue thee, Galate, when firſt of all</l>
                  <l>You with my mother came, to gather leaues of Crowtoe ſmall</l>
                  <l>Vpon our hil, when J as vſher, ſquirde you all the waie.</l>
                  <l>Nor when I ſawe thee firſt, nor afterward, nor at this daie,</l>
                  <l>Since then could J refraine; but you, by Joue, nought ſet thereby.</l>
                  <l>But well I knowe, fair Nimphe, the verie cauſe why you thus flie.</l>
                  <l>Becauſe vpon my front, one onlie brow, with briſtles ſtrong</l>
                  <l>From one eare to the other eare, is ſtretched al along.</l>
                  <l>Nethe which, one eie, and on my lips a hugie noſe there ſtandes.</l>
                  <l>Yet I, this ſuch a one, a thouſand ſheep ſeed on theſe lands.</l>
                  <l>And pleaſant milke I drinke, which from the ſtrouting bags is preſt.</l>
                  <l>Nor want I cheeſe in ſummer, nor in Autumne of the beſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet in winter time. my cheeſe-rackes euer laden are,</l>
                  <l>And better can I pipe, than anie Cyclops maie compare.</l>
                  <l>O Apple ſweet, of thee, and of my ſelfe, I vſe to ſing,</l>
                  <l>And that at midnight oft. for thee, aleavne faunes vp I bring,</l>
                  <l>All great with young, &amp; foure beares whelps, I nouriſh vp for thee.</l>
                  <l>But come thou hither firſt, and thou ſhalt haue them all of me.</l>
                  <l>And let the blewiſh colorde Sea beat on the ſhore ſo nie.</l>
                  <l>The night with me in caue, thou ſhalt conſume more pleaſantlie.</l>
                  <l>There are the ſhadie Baies, and there tall Cypres-trees doe ſprout,</l>
                  <l>And there is Juie blacke, and fertill Vines are al about.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:5"/>
                  <l>Coole water there J haue, diſtilled of the whiteſt ſnowe,</l>
                  <l>A drinke deuine, whiich out of wooddy Aetna mount doth flowe.</l>
                  <l>In theſe reſpects, who in the Sea &amp; waues would rather be?</l>
                  <l>But if J ſeeme as yet, too rough and ſauage vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>Great store of Oken woode I haue, and neuer quenched fire;</l>
                  <l>And J can well indure my ſoule to burne with thy deſire,</l>
                  <l>With this my onely eie, then which J nothing thinke more trimme.</l>
                  <l>Now woe is me, my mother bore me not with finns to ſwimme,</l>
                  <l>That J might diue to thee, that I thy dainty hand might kiſſe,</l>
                  <l>If lips thou wouldſt not let; then would J Lillies bring Jwis,</l>
                  <l>And tender Poppie toe, that beares a top like rattells red.</l>
                  <l>And theſe in ſummer time, but other are in winter bred,</l>
                  <l>So that I cannot bring them all at once. now certainlie,</l>
                  <l>Ile learne to ſwimme of ſome or other ſtranger paſſing bie,</l>
                  <l>That I maie knowe what pleaſure tis in waters deepe to dwell.</l>
                  <l>Come forth, faire Galate, and once got out, forget thee well</l>
                  <l>(As I doe ſitting on this rocke) home to returne againe.</l>
                  <l>But feede my ſheepe with me, &amp; for to milke them take the paine,</l>
                  <l>And cheeſe to preſſe, and in the milke, the rennet ſharpe to straine.</l>
                  <l>My mother only wrongeth me, and her I blame, for ſhee</l>
                  <l>Spake neuer yet to thee, one good or louelie worde of me,</l>
                  <l>And that, although ſhee daily ſees, how I awaie doe pine.</l>
                  <l>But I will ſaie my head and feete doe ake, that ſhee maie whine</l>
                  <l>And ſorrowe at the hart, becauſe my hart with griefe is ſwolne.</l>
                  <l>O Cyclops, Cyclops, whither is thy wit and reaſon flowne?</l>
                  <l>If thou wouldst baſkets make, and cut downe browzing from the tree,</l>
                  <l>And bring it to thy Lambes, a great deale wiſer thou ſhouldst be?</l>
                  <l>Goe coie ſome preſent Nimphe, why dost thou follow flying wind?</l>
                  <l>Perhaps an other Galate, and fairer thou ſhalt find.</l>
                  <l>For manie maidens in the euening tide with mee will plaie,</l>
                  <l>And all doe ſweetlie laugh, when I stand harkning what they ſaie,</l>
                  <l>And I ſome bodie ſeeme, and in the earth doe beare a ſwaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus Polyphemus ſinging, fed his raging loue of ould,</l>
                  <l>Wherein he ſweeter did, than had he ſent her ſummes of gould.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>POLYPHEM'S Embleme. <hi>Vbi Dictamum inueniam?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:5"/>
               <head>THE XVI. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>The ſtile of this Poeme is more loftie than anie of the reſt, &amp; Theocritus wrote it to Hiero king of Siracuſe in Sicily. Wherein hee reprooueth the nigardiſe of Princes and great men, towards the learned, and namelie Poets, in whoſe power it is, to make men famous to al poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Towards the end he praiſeth Hiero, and praieth that Sicilie may be deliuered, by his prowes, from the inuaſions of the Carthagineans. This Idillion is named Hiero, in reſpect of the Perſon to whome it was written, or Charites, that is Graces, in reſpect of the matter whereof it treateth.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>CHARITES, or HIERO.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>POETS</hi> haue ſtill this care, and ſtil the Muſes haue this care</l>
                  <l>To magnifie the Gods with ſonges, and men that worthy are.</l>
                  <l>The Muſes they are Goddeſes, and Gods with praiſe they crowne,</l>
                  <l>But we are mortall men, and mortall men let vs renowne.</l>
                  <l>But who of all the men, vnder the cope of heauen that dwell,</l>
                  <l>By opening of his dores, our Graces entertaines ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That vnrewarded quite he dothe not ſende them back agayne?</l>
                  <l>Thay in a chafe, al barefoote home to me returne with paine,</l>
                  <l>And me they greatly blame, &amp;, that they went for nought, they grutch,</l>
                  <l>And al to weary, in the bottome of an empty hutch,</l>
                  <l>Laying there heades vpon there knees full colde, they ſtill remaine,</l>
                  <l>Where they doe poorely dwell, becauſe they home returnde in vaine.</l>
                  <l>Of all that liuing are, who loues a man that ſpeaketh well?</l>
                  <l>I knowe not one; for now a daies for deedes that doe excell,</l>
                  <l>Men care not to be prayſde. But all are ouercum with gaine.</l>
                  <l>For euery man looks rounde, with hand in boſome, whence amaine</l>
                  <l>Coyne hee may get, whoſe ruſt rubde off, he wil not giue againe.</l>
                  <l>But ſtraite way thus he ſays; the legge is further then the knee,</l>
                  <l>Let me haue goulde inough, the Gods to Poets paie their fee.</l>
                  <l>Who would an other heere? Inough for al, one Homer is.</l>
                  <l>Of Poets he is prince, yet getts he nought of me Iwis.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mad men, what gaine is this to hoorde vp baggs of goulde within?</l>
                  <l>This is not monyes vſe, nor hath to wiſe men euer bin.</l>
                  <l>But part is due vnto our ſelues, part to the Poets pen,</l>
                  <l>And many kinsfolkes muſt be pleaſured, and many men,</l>
                  <l>And often to the Gods thou muſt doe ſolleme ſacrifiſe.</l>
                  <l>Nor muſt thou keep a ſparing houſe, but when in frendlie wiſe</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt receiued ſtrangers at thy boorde, when they will thence.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:6"/>
                  <l>Let them depart, but cheefely Poets muſt thou reuerence.</l>
                  <l>That after thou art hidden in thy graue, thou maiſt heere well,</l>
                  <l>Nor baſely maiſt thou mourne, when thou in Acharon doſt dwell;</l>
                  <l>Like to ſum ditcher vile, whoſe handes with worke are harde &amp; drie,</l>
                  <l>Who from his parentes poore, bewailes his life in beggerie.</l>
                  <l>In king Antiochus his Court, and king Aleuas toe,</l>
                  <l>To diſtribute the monthly bred, a many had to doe.</l>
                  <l>The Scopedans had many droues of calfes, which in their ſtales</l>
                  <l>Mong Oxen lowde, and ſhepeheardes kept in the Cranonian dales</l>
                  <l>Infinite flockes, to beare the hoſpital Creondan's charge.</l>
                  <l>No pleaſure ſhould theſe men enioy, of their expenſes large,</l>
                  <l>When ons their ſoules they had embarkt in the infernal Barge,</l>
                  <l>But leauing all this wealth behind, in wretched miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Among the dead, without renoune, for euer they ſhoulde lie,</l>
                  <l>Had not Simonides, the Chian Poet with his pen,</l>
                  <l>And with his Lute of many ſtringes, ſo famous made theſe men</l>
                  <l>To all poſteritie. the verie horſes are renoun'd,</l>
                  <l>Which from their races ſwift return'd, with olife garlandes crounde.</l>
                  <l>Who euer ſhoulde haue knowne the Lician Princes, and their race,</l>
                  <l>Or them of Troie, or Cignus with his womans color'd face,</l>
                  <l>Had not the Poets ſung the famous warrs of them of oulde?</l>
                  <l>Nor yet Vlyſſes (who for ten yeeres ſpace, on Seas was roulde</l>
                  <l>By ſundry ſorts of men, and who at laſt went downe to Hell</l>
                  <l>As yet aliue, and from the Cyclops den eſcaped well)</l>
                  <l>Had got ſuch laſting fame; and drounde ſhould lie in ſilence deepe</l>
                  <l>Swinehearde Eumæus, and Philætius, who had to keepe</l>
                  <l>A hearde of Nete; Laertes eke him ſelfe had bin vnknowne,</l>
                  <l>If far and wide their names, great Homers verſes had not blowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Immortal fame to mortal men the Muſes nine do giue.</l>
                  <l>But deade mens wealth is ſpent, and quite conſumde of them that liue.</l>
                  <l>But all one paine it is, to number waues vpon the bankes,</l>
                  <l>Wherof great ſtore, the winde from Sea, doth blowe to lande in rankes,</l>
                  <l>Or for to waſh a brick with water cleere, till it be white,</l>
                  <l>As for to moue a man, whome auarice doth ons delite.</l>
                  <l>Therefore adue to ſuch a one for me, and let him haue</l>
                  <l>Huge ſiluer heapes at will, and more and more ſtill let him craue;</l>
                  <l>But I, Goodwil of men, and Honor wil prefer, before</l>
                  <l>A many Mules of priſe, or many horſes kept in ſtore.</l>
                  <l>Therefore I aſke, to whom ſhall J be welcome with my traine</l>
                  <l>Of Muſes nine? whoſe waies are hard, if Joue guides not the raine.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The heauens yet haue not left to roule both monthes &amp; yeares on reeles,</l>
                  <l>And many horſes yet, ſhal turne about the Charret wheeles;</l>
                  <l>The man ſhall riſe, that ſhall haue neede of me, to ſet him out,</l>
                  <l>Doing ſuch deeds of armes, as Aiax, or Achilles stoute</l>
                  <l>Did in the fielde of Simois, where Ilus bones doe rest.</l>
                  <l>And now the Carthagineans, inhabiting the Weſt,</l>
                  <l>Who in the vtmoſt ende of Liby dwell, in armes are prest;</l>
                  <l>And now the Syracuſians their ſpeares doe carrie in the reſt.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe left-armes laden are with targets made of willoe tree.</l>
                  <l>Mongſt whom, king Hiero, the anchent Worthies match, I ſee</l>
                  <l>In armour ſhine, whoſe plume doth ouer ſhade his helmet bright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Iupiter, and thou Minerua fierce in fight,</l>
                  <l>And thou Proſerpina, who with thy mother, haſt renowne</l>
                  <l>By Lyſimelia ſtreames, in Ephyra that wealthy towne,</l>
                  <l>Out of our Iland driue our enimies, our bitter fate,</l>
                  <l>Along the Sardine Sea, that death of friends they maie relate</l>
                  <l>Vnto their children and their wiues, and that the townes oppreſt</l>
                  <l>By enimies, of th'old inhabitants maie be poſſeſt;</l>
                  <l>That they maie till the fields, and ſheepe vpon the downes maie blete</l>
                  <l>By thouſandes infinite, and fat, and that the heardes of Nete</l>
                  <l>As to their ſtalles they goe, maie preſse the lingring traueler.</l>
                  <l>Let groundes be broken vp for ſeede, what time the Graſhopper</l>
                  <l>Watching the ſheepheards by their flocks, in boughs cloſe ſinging lies;</l>
                  <l>And let the Spiders ſpread their ſlender webs in armories,</l>
                  <l>So that of warr, the verie name maie not be heard againe.</l>
                  <l>But let the Poets striue, king Hieros glories for to ſtraine</l>
                  <l>Beyonde the Scythean Sea, &amp; far beyond thoſe places, where</l>
                  <l>Semiramis did build thoſe ſtatelie walles, and rule did be are.</l>
                  <l>Mongſt whom, I will be one; for maine other men beſide</l>
                  <l>Joues daughters loue, whoſe studie still ſhal be, both far and wide</l>
                  <l>Sicilian Arethuſa, with the people, to aduance,</l>
                  <l>And warlike Hiero. Yee Graces, who keepe reſiance</l>
                  <l>In the Theſſalian mount Orchomenus, to Thebs of olde</l>
                  <l>So hateful, though of you belovde, to staie J wil be bolde,</l>
                  <l>Where I am bid to come, and I with them will stil remaine,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall inuite me to their houſe, with all my Muſes traine.</l>
                  <l>Nor you will I forſake; for what to men can louelie be</l>
                  <l>Without your companie? the Graces alwaies be with me.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Embleme. <hi>Sinihil attuleris, ibis Homere forás.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:7"/>
               <head>THE XVIII. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>Twelue noble Spartane Virgins are brought in ſinging in the euening at the chamber doore of Menelaus and Helena, on their wedding daie. And firſt they prettily ieſt with the Bridegroom, then they praiſe Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, laſtly they wiſh them both ioie of their marriage. Therefore this Idillio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is entitled Hellens Epithalamio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, Hellens wedding ſong.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>HELLENS Epithalamion.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>IN</hi> Sparta long agoe, where Menelaus wore the crowne,</l>
                  <l>Twelue noble Virgins, daughters to the greateſt in the towne,</l>
                  <l>All dight vpon their haire in Crowtoe garlands freſh and greene,</l>
                  <l>Danſt at the chamber doore of Helena the Queene,</l>
                  <l>What time this Menelay, the younger Sonne of Atreus,</l>
                  <l>Did marry with this louely daughter of Prince Tyndarus.</l>
                  <l>And therewithal at eve, a wedding ſong they iointly ſung,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a ſhuffling of their feets, that all the Pallace rung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fair Bridegrome, do you ſleep? hath ſlumber al your lims poſſeſt?</l>
                  <l>What, are you drouſie? or hath wine your bodie ſo oppreſt</l>
                  <l>That you are gone to bed? for if you needes would take your rest,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould haue tane a ſeaſon meete. meane time, till it be daie</l>
                  <l>Suffer the Bride with vs, and with her mother deere to plaie.</l>
                  <l>For, Menelaus, ſhee at euening and at morning tide,</l>
                  <l>From daie to daie, and yeare to yeare ſhall be thy louing Bride.</l>
                  <l>O happie Bridegrome, ſure ſome honest man did ſneze to thee</l>
                  <l>When thou to Sparta came, to meete with ſuch a one as ſhee.</l>
                  <l>Among the demi-gods thou only art accounted meete</l>
                  <l>To be the Sonne in lawe of Joue; for vnderneath one ſheete</l>
                  <l>His daughter lies with thee. of al that tread on ground with feet</l>
                  <l>There is not ſuch a one in Greece. now ſure ſum goodlie thing</l>
                  <l>Shee will thee beare, if it be like the mother that ſhee bring.</l>
                  <l>For we her peeres in age, whoſe courſe of life is evne the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Who at Eurotas ſtreames, like men are oiled to the game,</l>
                  <l>And foure times ſixtie maides, of all the weemen youth we are,</l>
                  <l>Of theſe none wants a fault, if her with Hellen we compare.</l>
                  <l>Like as the riſing Morning ſhewes a gratefull lightening,</l>
                  <l>When ſacred night is past, and winter nowe lets looſe the ſpring;</l>
                  <l>So glittering Hellen ſhinde among the maides, luſtie and tal;</l>
                  <l>As is the furrowe in a field that far out-ſtretcheth al,</l>
                  <l>Or in a garden is a Cypreſ-tree, or in a trace</l>
                  <l>A ſteede of Theſſalie, ſo ſhee to Sparta was a grace.</l>
                  <l>No damſell with ſuch workes as ſhee, her baskets vſde to fill,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:7"/>
                  <l>Nor in a diuerſe color'd web, a woofe, of greater skill</l>
                  <l>Doth cut off from the loome, nor anie hath ſuch ſongs and laies</l>
                  <l>Vnto her daintie harpe, in Dians and Mineruas praiſe</l>
                  <l>As Hellen hath, in whoſe bright eies, all Loues and Graces be.</l>
                  <l>O faire, ô louelie maide, a matrone now is made of thee.</l>
                  <l>But wee wil evrie ſpring, vnto the leaues in meadowes goe,</l>
                  <l>To gather Garlands ſweete, and there not with a little woe</l>
                  <l>Will often thinke of thee, O Hellen, as the ſucking Lamms</l>
                  <l>Deſire the strouting baggs, and preſence of their tender damms.</l>
                  <l>We all betimes for thee, a wreath of Melitoe will knit,</l>
                  <l>And on a ſhadie Plane, for thee will ſafelie faſten it.</l>
                  <l>And all betimes for thee, vnder a ſhadie Plane below,</l>
                  <l>Out of a ſiluer boxe the ſweeteſt ointment will beſtowe.</l>
                  <l>And letters ſhall bee written in the barke, that men maie ſee,</l>
                  <l>And reade, Doe humble reuerence, for J am Hellens tree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweete Bride, good night, &amp; thou, O happy Bridegroome, now good night,</l>
                  <l>Latona ſend you happie iſſue, who is moſt of might</l>
                  <l>In helping youth, and bliſfull Venus ſend you equall loue</l>
                  <l>Bitwixt you both, and Ioue giue laſting riches from aboue,</l>
                  <l>Which from your noble ſelues, vnto your noble impes may fall.</l>
                  <l>Sleepe on, and breath into your breſts deſiers mutuall.</l>
                  <l>But in the morning wake, forget it not in anie wiſe.</l>
                  <l>And we wil then returne as ſoone as anie one ſhall riſe,</l>
                  <l>And in the chamber ſtur, and firſt of all lift vp the hed.</l>
                  <l>Hymen, O Hymen, now be gladſome at this marrige bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Embleme. <hi>Vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adeo latet vtilitas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>THE XXI. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>A Neteheard is brought in chaſing, that Eunîca a maid of the cittie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to kiſſe him. Wherby it is thought that Theocritus ſeemeth to checke them, that thinke this kinde of writing in Poetry, to be too baſe &amp; ruſtical. And therfore this Poeme is termed Neteheard.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>NETEHEARDE.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>EVNÎCA</hi> ſkorned me, when her I would haue ſweetly kist,</l>
                  <l>And railing at me ſaid, goe with a miſchiefe where thou list.</l>
                  <l>Thinkst thou a wretched Neteheard mee to kiſſe? I haue no will</l>
                  <l>After the Countrie guiſe to ſmouch, of Citie lips I ſkill.</l>
                  <l>My louely mouth, ſo much as in thy dreame thou ſhalt not touch.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2784:8"/>
                  <l>How dost thou look? How doſt thou talke? How plaieſt thou the ſlouch?</l>
                  <l>How daintilie thou ſpeakst? What courting words thou bringeſt out?</l>
                  <l>Howe ſoft a beard thou haſt? How faire thy locks hang round about?</l>
                  <l>Thy lips are like a ſickmans lips, thy hands, ſo black they be,</l>
                  <l>And rankely thou doſt ſmel, awaie, leaſt thou defileſt me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hauing thus ſed, ſhee ſpatterd on her boſome twiſe or thriſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill beholding me from top to toe, in skorneful wiſe,</l>
                  <l>She mutterd with her lips, and with her eies ſhe lookte aſide,</l>
                  <l>And of her beutie wondrous coy ſhe was, her mouth ſhe wride,</l>
                  <l>And proudly mockt me to my face. my blud boild in each vaine,</l>
                  <l>And red I woxe for griefe, as doth the roſe with dewye raine.</l>
                  <l>Thus leauing me, awaie ſhe flung; ſince when, it vexeth me,</l>
                  <l>That J ſhould be ſo skornde, of ſuch a filthie drab as ſhe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ye Shepeheards, tel me true, am I not fair as any ſwan?</l>
                  <l>Hath of a ſodaine anie God, made me another man?</l>
                  <l>For well J wote before, a cumlie grace in me did ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Like Iuy round about a tree, and dekt this bearde of mine.</l>
                  <l>My criſped lockes, like Parſlie on my temples wont to ſpred,</l>
                  <l>And on my eiebrowes black, a milke white forhed gliſtered.</l>
                  <l>More ſeemelie were mine eies, than are Mineruas eies I know.</l>
                  <l>My mouth for ſweetnes paſſed cheeſe, and from my mouth did flow</l>
                  <l>A voice more ſweete than hunniecombes. Sweete is my rundelaie,</l>
                  <l>When on the whiſtle, flute, or pipe, or cornet I doe plaie.</l>
                  <l>And all the weemen on our hills, doe ſaie that I am faire,</l>
                  <l>And al do loue me well. But theſe that breath the citty aire</l>
                  <l>Did neuer loue me yet. And why? The cauſe is this I know,</l>
                  <l>That I a Neteheard am. They heare not, how in vales below</l>
                  <l>Faire Bacchus kept a heard of beaſtes; nor can theſe nice ones tell,</l>
                  <l>How Venus rauing for a Neteheards loue, with him did dwell</l>
                  <l>Vpon the hills of Phrygia, and how ſhe lovde againe</l>
                  <l>Adonis in the woods, and mournde in woods, when hee was ſlaine.</l>
                  <l>What was Endymion? Was he not a Netehearde? Yet the Moone</l>
                  <l>Did love this Neteheard ſo, that from the heauens deſcending ſoone,</l>
                  <l>She came to Latmos groue, where with the daintie lad ſhe laie.</l>
                  <l>And Rhea, thou a Neteheard doſt bewaile, and thou al daie</l>
                  <l>O mightie Jupiter, but for a Shepeheardes boie didst straie.</l>
                  <l>Eunica only dained not, a Neteheard for to loue.</l>
                  <l>Better forſooth then Cybel, Venus, or the Moone aboue.</l>
                  <l>And Venus, thou hereafter muſt not loue thy faire Adone</l>
                  <l>In cittie, nor on hill, but al the night muſt ſleepe alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Embleme. <hi>Habitarunt Dij quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Syluas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:2784:8"/>
               <head>THE XXXI. JDILLION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>Argument.</head>
                  <p>The conceit of this Idillion is verie delicate. Wherein it is imagined, how Venus did ſend for the Bore, who in hunting ſlew Adonis, a dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yuth, whom ſhe loued; And how the Bore aunſwering for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he ſlew him againſt his wil, as beeing inamored on him, &amp; thinking onlie to kiſſe his naked thigh, ſhe forgaue him. The Poets drift is, to ſhew the power of loue, not onlie in men, but alſo in brute beaſts. Although in the two laſt verſes, by the burning of the Bores amorous teeth, he intimateth, that extrauagant and vnorderly paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are to be reſtrained by reaſon.</p>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <head>ADONIS.</head>
                  <l>WHEN <hi>VENVS</hi> firſt did ſee,</l>
                  <l>Adonis dead to be,</l>
                  <l>With woeful tatterd heare,</l>
                  <l>And cheekes ſo wan and ſeare,</l>
                  <l>The winged Loues ſhe bad,</l>
                  <l>The Bore ſhould straight be had.</l>
                  <l>Forthwith like birdes thay flie,</l>
                  <l>And through the wood thay hie.</l>
                  <l>The woefull beast thay finde,</l>
                  <l>And him with cordes thay binde.</l>
                  <l>One with a rope before,</l>
                  <l>Doth lead the captiue Bore.</l>
                  <l>Another on his backe,</l>
                  <l>Doth make his bow to cracke.</l>
                  <l>The beaſt went wretchedly,</l>
                  <l>For Venus horribly</l>
                  <l>Hee fearde, who thus him curst.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of all the beaſts the wurſt,</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou this thigh ſo wounde?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou my Loue confounde?</l>
                  <l>The beaſt thus ſpake in feare;</l>
                  <l>Venus, to thee J ſweare,</l>
                  <l>By thee, and huſband thine,</l>
                  <l>And by theſe bands of mine,</l>
                  <l>And by theſe hunters all,</l>
                  <l>Thy huſband faire and tall,</l>
                  <l>J minded not to kill,</l>
                  <l>But as an image ſtill,</l>
                  <l>J him beheld for loue,</l>
                  <l>Which made me forward ſhoue,</l>
                  <l>His thigh, that naked was,</l>
                  <l>Thinking to kiſſe alas.</l>
                  <l>And that hath hurt me thus.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherfore theſe teeth, Venus,</l>
                  <l>Or puniſh, or cut out.</l>
                  <l>Why beare I in my ſnowt,</l>
                  <l>Theſe needleſſe teeth about?</l>
                  <l>If this maie not ſuffiſe,</l>
                  <l>Cut off my chaps likewiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ruth he Venus moues,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe commands the Loues,</l>
                  <l>His bands for to vntie.</l>
                  <l>After, he came not nie</l>
                  <l>The wood, but at her wil,</l>
                  <l>He followde Venus still.</l>
                  <l>And cumming to the fire,</l>
                  <l>He burnt vp his deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Embleme. <hi>Raris forma viris, ſęcula proſpice, Impunita fuit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
